Bring young Gawain here.
把小高文带来
The king would speak with you.
国王要和你谈谈
Where is thy mother?
你妈妈在哪
She was not feeling herself, my lord.
她感到不舒服 殿下
Then come. Sit here, besides us.
那就过来 坐这里 挨着我们
Besides me and my queen.
挨着我和王后
That is not my place.
那不是属于我的位置
No. Let it be, today.
不 今天就随它去吧
Its owner is away.
它的主人不在
Who knows when he will return?
谁知道他什么时候回来呢
Please.
请吧
Good to see you, Gawain.
很高兴见到你 高文
Good to have one's family by one's side.
有家人在身旁真好
One's blood.
血脉
Surely your knights have spilled enough blood in your name
你的骑士们以你的名义流了足够多的血
to bind them closer to you than I.
他们比我更亲近于你
True.
对
But you are my sister's boy,
但你是我姐姐的孩子
queefed from her womb.
由她的子宫生出
They are not.
他们不是
I look out upon my friends here today
今天在这里 我看着我的朋友们
and I see... songs... no muse could ever sing or dream of.
我看到了 所有缪斯都不曾唱或梦见的歌
But I turn to thee and I see what?
但我看向你 却看到了什么
I recognize but I do not know thee.
我认识你 却不了解你
I say this not in reproach, but regret that
我说这些不是责备 而是在遗憾
I have never asked you to sit at my side before this day
我不曾让你坐在我身边 直到今天
or upon my knee when thy was newborn.
或者在你出生不久 能伏在我膝头
But now it is Christmas,
但今天是圣诞日
and I wish to build bridges.
我想搭起桥梁
So before we make merry...
所以在我们寻乐子前
you make for me a gift.
你为我准备一份礼物吧
You tell me a tale of yourself,
你告诉我一个关于你的故事
so that I might know thee.
好让我了解你
I have none to tell, King.
我没有什么好讲的 殿下
Yet.
还没有
You have none to tell yet.
你还没有什么要讲的
Look around you, young Gawain.
看看你周围 小高文
What do you see?
你看到了什么
I see legends.
我看到了传说们
Do not take your place amongst them idly.
不要在他们中间无所事事
Hmm.
嗯
So who else then... hmm?
那么接着到谁 嗯
Friends...
朋友们
Brothers... (Brothers...) Brothers and... sisters all. (…sisters all)
兄弟们和姐妹们
I thank thee for breaking bread with me this blessed day.
我感谢你们在受福之日与我分食面包
And it is blessed...
它是神圣的
for out my window this morn I looked,
因为今早我望向窗外
and I saw a land shaped...by your hands.
我看到了由你们双手所塑的土地的形状
You have lain those same hands upon our Saxon brethren,
你们以同样的手伸向我们撒克逊的弟兄们
who now in your shadow bow their heads like babes.
如今在你们的阴影下 他们像婴孩般低头
Peace, peace you have brought to your kingdom,
和平 这由你们为你们的王国带来的和平
so it is in peace that I... I now say to you...
所以在这和平里 我此刻告诉你们
that I... I am the luckiest here today...
我是最幸运之人
because I am amongst thee.
因为我在你们中间
I am amongst thee.
我与你们同在
So before we celebrate the birth of our Christ,
所以在我们庆祝我们的基督诞生前
let us honor one of our own who has done great things in His name.
让我们敬奉他的名行了大事的我们每一个人
So a tale, or... Or a show perhaps.
所以说一个故事 或者一场表演
What have thee?
你们有什么
Who can regale me and my queen
谁能取悦我和王后
with some myth or canto of thine own purport?
用关于你们自己的神话或篇章